The International Olympic Committee has the honour of announcing that the
21st Olympic Winter Games in 2010 are awarded to the city of
Vancouver.
This is my perfect city,
Vancouver,
Canada.
Vancouver has been chosen by an influential British magazine as the world's most livable city.
Vancouver has come out on top in a survey of 130 cities around the world.
It's really not hard to see why Vancouver is considered one of the best.
This is the fifth year in a row that Vancouver has topped this list.
But take one wrong turn and you're in the roughest area in North America.
Vancouver's downtown east side guest.
I just got a bottle broken over my head.
Who the fuck threw that?
As I was saying,
this is the roughest neighborhood in North America.
One out of every three homeless people living here have AIDS.
Two out of three people have Hep C.
It has the highest crime rate per capita in North America.
Living conditions are on par with Botswana,
Africa,
a third world country.
How can this place be known as the best city in the world?
The disparity between this neighborhood and Vancouver's reputation as one of the world's most livable cities is disturbing.
We have this horrible secret that is the Downtown Eastside.
The most concentrated area of drug use in all of North America.
Many people aren't aware that this community experienced the most explosive HIV epidemic ever seen in the developed world.
Alcohol,
drugs,
HIV,
hepatitis C,
in the last decade that's what we're seeing a lot of.
How as a society did we get into this situation in the first place?
In all this mess,
what am I doing to help my city?
Well,
I wake up,
I sing,
I study,
and I stress.
But I don't make a difference.
Sure,
sometimes I talk about the issues with friends at school,
padding my academic ego with stats from the morning's paper.
But,
as always,
that frail state of caring dissipates.
Gotta go back to class,
lunch,
nap,
dinner,
movie,
sleep.
It's all so familiar.
But one day everything changed.
While having lunch with a friend on the force,
I presented my opinion on homelessness.
Living on the streets is easy.
They don't want to work.
They're a bunch of scammers.
They can get a job like everybody else and work a nine-to-five.
They don't want to do that.
They got everything they need just living there on the street.
You got no idea,
man.
I say,
what you want to do?
Go down there for 30 days?
All my friends say,
I want to go on some crazy vacation.
I say,
you know what?
Go get a room down there,
and then we'll see what it's all about.
She went on about the gang wars,
drug busts,
shootings,
but I wasn't listening.
All I could hear was one tiny,
horrible word.
Go.
I couldn't shake it.
School,
work,
rent,
get HIV,
shot,
stabbed.
Go.
By the time the beer hit my lips,
it was decided.
For 31 days in December,
I will conduct a social experiment on myself.
I will totally abandon my predictable life and attempt to survive the streets of Vancouver.
do you know where there's any place where I can get food and shelter around here?
Leaving behind my possessions,
I...
identity,
friends,
and family.
My goal is to confront the challenges of street life firsthand,
so I see how hard it really is.
This experiment,
I hope,
will shed light on a crisis that is spiraling out of control.
And well,
instead of crossing a bridge downtown,
I'm swimming,
so I start my journey freezing,
wet,
and naked.
I arrived downtown with nothing but a backpack with a hidden video camera inside.
The temperature was around the freezing mark,
but thankfully the rain stopped.
My first challenge was to find city services offering food,
shelter and clothing.
I had no idea where to look,
so I went to Granville Street to ask the locals.
Someone had to know.
Hey you guys,
do you guys know a place right here where I can get some free food and shelter?
Know where I can get some free food and shelter?
No idea.
0:05:41.679,0:04:19.960
Hey man,
Well there's a gallery there,
it's just two blocks.
Two blocks down?
Thanks a lot man.
Enter the Gathering Place,
a resource centre for the homeless.
When I walked through the door,
they told me I was hypothermic and threw me into a hot shower.
They gave me some clothes and told me to go talk to the guy at the front counter when I was done.
So,
tell me everything I get.
You get everything that we do at the place.
So you get to go to the laundry rooms,
the pool rooms,
the video game rooms,
the showers,
the...
Clothing donation area,
jacuzzi,
we're on fitness classes.
What about yoga?
Do I get yoga?
we have a yoga class.
I couldn't believe all the luxury services there were for the homeless.
This place had live music,
snooker,
martial arts,
and let's not forget the therapeutic hot tub.
The mineral-rich hydrotherapy relaxed my muscles.
Alright,
enough fooling around,
I'm starving.
And lucky for me,
December is Christmas time,
and all the charities are loaded with good food.
When I finally found the place,
on my first night's menu,
turkey,
gravy,
mashed potatoes,
corn,
all washed down.
with a hot chocolate and apple crumble pie.
Next,
I had to find somewhere to sleep.
I asked around,
and Matt,
a homeless guy,
helped me out.
He told me he was staying at a really nice place,
the Yukon Homeless Shelter.
So I tagged along and got a bed.
Since he didn't want to be on camera,
he agreed to film me.
All right,
it's time to do laundry.
Laundry's pretty simple.
Need to find the door here.
Come and pick this up,
cleans it,
the next time you see that,
everything in there will be clean.
Beautiful.
Can't go wrong when you're homeless.
well,
it's time to go to bed.
There you go.
Quality treatment.
I'm never going home.
So at the end of day one,
I had accomplished a lot.
Food,
shelter,
clothing were all taken care of.
I even had yoga.
The next morning,
I felt fantastic.
My bed was really comfortable,
and breakfast and coffee waited downstairs.
But first,
it's time for a bubble bath.
So now that I'm fresh and clean,
I went out on the town to talk fashion with the locals.
Based on my appearance,
what would you guess that I do for a living?
I'll be working one of these stores.
I would think you work in a bureau or something.
Your shoes suck.
My sock is worth more than your entire outfit.
You guys just smiled but not enough whiteness happening.
Get some colour happening,
buddy.
Like it's freaking dying out there.
Get some f*****g...
There it is.
If I want to live off people's handouts for the rest of the month,
looking like a gay fashion coordinator isn't going to cut it.
I had to develop a daily routine for getting dirty.
Let's get dirty.
Alright,
here we are at 2088 Yukon Street,
home of
Vancouver's finest homeless people,
including Misha right here.
These guys would have taken me in though with a regular jacket.
Oh,
here's trouble,
here's trouble.
How do you like living in a homeless shelter?
Oh,
I love it every minute of it.
Building social housing.
And housing bumps generously is not going to solve the problem.
It's going to create an additional influx of thousands and thousands of people who want to lead this kind of life.
Do not make such a life.
tempting a big reason the guys at the shelter are so happy is because today is welfare day and i want a piece of the action this is how you do it step one go to the welfare office there you will be told to get diagnosed for a mental
illness
which will grant you welfare without having to seek employment.
Without this diagnosis,
you'll have to prove you've been looking for a job,
and that's way too much work.
Step 2.
Check into your local mental health center and get your diagnosis.
Now this is the tricky part.
How does a guy without a mental illness get diagnosed with a mental illness?
Easy.
Just tell the doctor you're always depressed.
She'll diagnose you with chronic depression,
give you a handful of happy pills,
and send you on your way.
Step 3.
Fill out the welfare application at your local library.
Step 4.
The application will require the signature of a landlord who will rent to a welfare recipient.
No problem.
Step 5.
Cash welfare check at your local money.
Mart.
Step six,
spend all the money on something essential.
Cheers.
When you're hungover,
there's nothing like a greasy burger.
And after gorging myself at a community barbecue,
I bumped into Gerald,
the self-declared lyrical gangster of East Vancouver.
When you compete with me,
I feel like Al Capone.
I control this town.
Yo,
maestro,
it's a showdown,
it's a control down.
If I work hard,
tell me what I work.
Don't play me low.
Times are tough these days.
I don't rob nobody in the street.
If I do rob,
I rob from the rich.
What do you do?
You don't know what the fuck you're doing here.
It's so squat.
Squat?
Where you live in?
West Bank?
West
Bank? No.
Yeah,
I thought so.
I can't tell.
Rich white folks.
You can tell.
Squat,
right?
You can still tell?
I don't know what you want.
How do you tell that I'm rich white folks?
You can tell,
man.
The way you try to tell.
It's just the way.
You're so proper.
It's like when you go to military school.
Yeah.
Even when you go back out in real life,
you still have that.
Because they train you,
right?
They train you all the way.
So you got that posture,
that stress.
Just relax and lose,
man.
Don't make a sound.
Don't wear no watch.
Don't smoke,
down,
don't do nothing like that.
Gerald's right.
I've been living on the street for 10 days now and I still don't fit in.
It's because my life here is really easy.
Whenever I want free clothes,
I go get them.
Whenever I want free food,
I go to the charities.
You know,
I even ride the bus for free.
Just get on,
say I have no money.
It's easy.
Now the thing I don't get is why a lot of the homeless don't use these free services on the regular.
Why make life so hard on yourself?
I don't know.
But maybe if I make life a bit harder on myself,
I'll find the answer.
So no more bubble baths.
It's time to make money the hard way,
by working for it.
Besides,
my welfare check's spent.
And the boys say the big money's in squeegeeing.
So I stole one and got to work.
Although profitable,
squeegeeing was abusive,
dangerous,
and demeaning.
So I thought I'd try panhandling.
Panhandling
wasn't my gig.
I didn't make that much money.
Plus it was boring and cold.
So why not search for empties in the city's bins?
After all,
one man's garbage can be another man's pleasure.
I need some privacy.
Camera person,
turn it off.
I got cut up and stinky for low pay.
You rifle through dog crap,
vomit,
use condoms,
trying to find anything of value.
Get pricked by a disease needle and you're dead.
I asked Brian how he felt about binning.
He showed me there's dignity in it.
This is probably some lifesaver for me.
Is this a saver for me?
Yeah,
it really is.
I know that sounds retarded to the average guy.
I don't need to do this job.
But for now...
I'm going to make a lot of shots.
But for now,
This is probably all fake.
Yeah,
it really is.
Whether the public knows it or not,
this is saving the public big money.
Because it costs like 80 grand to keep a guy in prison.
A guy's not,
he can't do this.
Like,
if he takes the bottles away,
he costs the alleys or whatever.
Yeah.
it's a lot of work.
Yeah,
like if you figure out the money.
I've been out for 11 years.
Since 97 I got out.
So,
if you figure out the amount of money that I've saved...
Basically by spending.
It's saving the government.
It really is.
If you recycle,
88...
88 million?
88 million.
Yeah.
And that's been hanging up here since I've been here.
This bottle depot was founded by a binner and serves only downtown Eastside residents.
And believe me,
it gets used.
It generates $2 million a year for the binners.
One morning's worth of recycling.
With the little money I made binning,
I decided to treat myself.
Double Big Mac meal,
supersized.
Six McNuggets and a large hot chocolate.
And that's when I met Captain Tone.
Sir,
you're going to my machine.
I can't do that.
not no more.
Close the door.
It's cold.
buddy.
Close the door.
You're fucking...
You're not going to get a thing.
Can you close the door?
No.
Hey Get out of here.
You have to do this.
Well,
I think Vancouver is an interesting but disturbing social experiment.
Policymakers convinced many people working with the mentally ill that they would take the mentally ill out of institutions like Riverview.
In 2005,
Riverview,
one of the largest mental hospitals in North America,
transferred thousands of patients into downtown Vancouver.
Expected to be more independent,
the mentally ill would go unsupervised,
live in a more home-like setting,
and become part of the community,
like a normal citizen.
Unfortunately,
they were basically left to fend for themselves.
The community supports weren't there.
The community mental health agencies were overrun and understaffed and inability to meet demand.
And people ended up coming here,
just like people always have,
to find cheap,
affordable housing.
When I returned to the Yukon shelter,
they told me my time was up.
They sent me away with a list of other emergency shelters.
I had no idea what I was in for.
If you want to pick ten things that determine why people are healthy or unhealthy...
Well,
housing makes the list every single time.
And the housing that is available to most people living in poverty is completely substandard.
You know,
when you have a large number of people sharing a single space and you have this increased prevalence of infectious diseases,
it is a risky place for some people.
And that's what we see in the hospital.
People are getting infections in their skin and their legs,
also pneumonia,
gastroenteritis.
Bed 40?
no,
Shit.
Bed 50.
Okay.
You guys have to get your beds straight up here.
Alright.
Okay.
From down the hallway,
I hear a symphony of horking phlegm and blaring rock and roll.
The smell of fermenting feet and bed bug pesticide made me gag.
Guys were vomiting in the bathroom sinks.
The lineup was 30 minutes long to use the washroom.
How on earth could anyone sleep in here?
I can see why a lot of the homeless prefer to sleep outside.
Some hear the stink,
others the snoring.
For me it's the phlegm.
The guy in the bed next to mine spat mouthfuls onto the floor all night.
It was absolute torture.
In the morning,
thank God for the morning,
I bumped into Stuart and asked his opinion on the shelters.
I don't like shelters.
They remind me of prison too much.
The attitude,
the atmosphere,
It's the same thing as prison.
Couple nights later,
I began puking and had explosive diarrhea.
The lady at the desk nodded like she'd seen this before,
and checked me into emergency right away.
It's disgusting.
Fucking disgusting.
I feel like shit.
At the homeless shelter there's always the token guy that keeps everybody up all night shitting,
vomiting,
coughing,
horking,
and smiting.
Well last night at the shelter I was that guy.
When you're that guy you don't really care about keeping other people up,
all you care about is feeling better.
It really brings things into perspective.
The doctor took forever.
When he did arrive,
He had bad news.
I had a severe case of gastroenteritis,
a viral infection causing inflammation in the stomach and intestines.
Symptoms include diarrhea,
vomiting,
headache,
fever,
and abdominal cramps.
He gave me some codeine,
a whack load of T3s,
and sent me on my way.
I need to find shit to make my bed because I'm not going back to the emergency shelter the doctor told me I can get even more sick and I'm not getting more sick so I'm sleeping on the street from here on in and I'm trying to find shit with
this,
trying to find ancient bedding with this wonderful music in the background what is this shit?
this is kinda weird holy fuck holy shit,
there's a fucking rat in there,
that's disgusting
This will be great for sleeping on.
Some cardboard.
Jackpot.
Does it have all the wheels too?
Well kind of.
Yeah that's the catch.
Oh,
yes.
Well,
I'm gonna steal this homeless guy's shit.
Perfect.
I got my blankets.
Alright,
well...
This is where I'm going to bed.
It's as good as any.
My
stomach hurts.
I feel bloated.
I have to go to the washroom.
This is just gross.
There's piss all around me.
There's junkies everywhere.
I want to get out of here.
I'm going to go find a nice place where I can actually get some sleep.
This is too gross.
I can't sleep here.
Because I felt so sick,
I had no appetite.
This made things easy.
That is until the clouds rolled in with the Vancouver rain.
I couldn't find a good spot on the cover.
I just wanted to sleep.
Oh,
look at that.
It's like the fucking jackpot of emergency shelter.
It looks like a cave.
And it looks like we have a visitor as well.
Another,
Obviously...
This is the residence of homeless person X and Y.
So,
time to be Zed.
I'm gonna...
Look at this,
this is like,
this is like too good.
It looks contrived.
Fuck it.
It was Christmas Eve and all I wanted was a bed to sleep on,
so I cheated.
On a prayer,
I went to the Yukon shelter and somehow got a room.
Yes,
an entire room.
The sleep was simply glorious.
When the morning came,
I cleaned myself up,
went downstairs,
and what do you know?
Santa gives presents to the homeless too.
All of these presents came from local charities,
so it's time to cash in.
Looks like a nice jacket too.
That looks like a nice fleece.
Yeah.
Yeah,
I think so.
Perfect.
Steve,
you got something to say?
I scored an extra goal,
an extra pair of pants,
and an extra underwear.
Your bucket is going down there.
We're going to be loaded today.
And see this beautiful thing right here?
It doesn't fit him.
It doesn't fit me,
so I'm going to have to sell it.
And sponsor my little habit.
And the retail price is one 10-rock for one jacket.
So no,
I'm not in favor of just throwing money at them.
If we get too generous about this,
we create ecological niches that actually compel them to this kind of life.
So all those people who have bleeding hearts and say people really have no choice,
they are born in a certain socioeconomic class and that determines where they will end up,
should remind themselves that that also commits them to saying an incentive structure that makes it easy
to become a bum determines that these people will make those bad decisions.
You guys think most of these guys spent their Christmas gifts on crack?
No,
I think,
0:26:58.909,0:26:49.470
I'm Steven,
I think all of those guys did.
Do you think they do it every Christmas?
I think every year,
yeah.
Most of them or not all though?
Birthdays,
Christmas.
I think most of them,
yeah.
And I think that's the only reason we're really happy right now is because if the four of us were walking over the bridge and we had no drugs,
no money,
and no merchandise to sell,
we wouldn't be this happy.
We wouldn't be filming.
One of us would probably be trying to save the other from jumping off this bridge.
That's the way it is.
There's not a lot of legitimate opportunities for people to make money sometimes,
and of course there's a shadow economy or a street economy that operates all around this.
This is the system that people are navigating or maneuvering within.
Whether I like it or not,
the homeless share it.
our unique top priority.
Something I've never tried.
Hardcore drugs.
Specifically crack and heroin.
I can't hide from this reality anymore.
So for the last six days of my journey,
I'm going to get high with the rest.
Like everything else,
to truly understand it,
I have to do it.
Wish me luck.
Vancouver has one of the world's most notorious open drug scenes,
and it's been that way for a long time.
It's very unique here because in other cities,
there's not such a concentration of people who are using illicit substances or illicit drugs.
When people visit Vancouver from big American cities that have large drug problems,
they're always shocked by how open it is here in Vancouver.
it is here in Vancouver.
Everything's just right out on the street.
I went to meet the guys in Crack Alley,
where they said they'd be getting their fix.
0:38:37.136,0:28:37.821
When I arrived,
0:38:37.897,0:28:38.962
it was full of addicts,
0:38:39.678,0:28:41.104
but hard to find what I was looking for.
well,
don't do that,
because I'm not going to let you do it.
It'd be stupid.
You'd be an idiot to do that.
Give me that later.
Say you smoke that crack and then you smoke it every once in a while and start skipping school.
Then you'll never pass your class.
And then you have to think it like that.
Just don't put that camera on anybody else over here.
We didn't want to mess around,
so we went over to the other side.
And that's where I met Crystal,
the matriarch of the alley.
She hooked me up with Crack.
So this is too much?
Yeah,
you don't want to put...
I'd say a third.
So can you just break it like you're doing?
Yeah.
Use a blade.
So I put the rock in here?
I love you,
brother.
too.
I'm homeless and high in the nastiest alley in the city,
but now I feel at home.
Suddenly these drug addicts,
these complete strangers,
like family.
Ha.
I'm falling.
Are you falling?
I love rock.
I was only 15 years and I have no attention.
Yo.
Wait,
now I have to go.
Yeah,
that's really nice.
I come from a good family.
Right?
These things is a drug in itself.
But now the high's gone.
Changing the alley back to the sad place it really is.
I want more.
But luckily,
Humphrey was dealing crack right next to me.
While hooking me up with the 10 Rock,
Humphrey told me how he ended up down here.
One day,
I had some friends over to my house.
And...
And,
Courtesy,
I took out some dope and I gave it to them.
My fiance was coming home from a weekend in Whistler and she worked for a law firm,
which is a law firm in downtown.
And she was like,
what's going on?
And I'm like...
My dad's a doctor.
I couldn't say anything,
My mom's an accountant.
it was so fucking hot.
I was adopted.
I had three walls of fucking dough cooked and hidden on top of the dressing.
My sister was murdered by Robert Pickton.
She had an addiction.
And she's like,
I ended up coming down here.
I can't stay here,
I can't stay here.
I'm here downtown Eastside because I choose to be.
So she leaves and I'm thinking,
oh great,
There an addiction.
0:31:53.891,0:30:54.331
I ended up coming down here.
she'll be back.
Her parents lived on Grand Valley and she went there for herself.
It's an addiction.
0:31:56.922,0:31:00.503
Getting off of these things is as hard as getting off of crap.
So the next thing you know is that when she came back,
she came back to pack her stuff.
I couldn't understand the addiction to heroin and people getting sick,
but it's a drug that you need,
right?
Listen,
It comes to the point that you don't want it.
like,
You literally cannot move.
It's a piece of shit.
It's like,
It's like peace for you.
The first time I did it,
It's like,
you know what I mean?
First time I did it,
it was the most amazing feeling I ever had that I puked for like 60 hours.
Every time you puke,
you get more high.
Oh,
really?
So you look forward to puking?
Yeah.
now I do.
It's a really good job.
it was really good time.
But I OD'd the other day right there on that corner.
And you know what?
Nobody called 911 because they had dope over there.
They were digging me.
I know how hard it is.
I know you can test,
like,
doing my hair.
The addictive liability of these drugs is evident in how much health-related harm and suffering people are willing to endure as a result of their drug use.
People think that,
you know,
simply throwing more police and throwing...
people in jail will actually deter people from seeking that reward of their high.
If you're willing to die for the high,
well,
going in jail isn't going to stop it either.
To watch the police roll up and watch a bunch of people that are injecting scatter,
you can really see that it doesn't have much impact on the problem.
It's basically displacing it.
And I've heard some police officers refer to this as shoveling water.
As Crystal predicted,
I felt horrible and cold.
So I bundled up and took a breather.
Coming down from crack is that feeling when the world hates you and all you want to do is cry.
But knowing my next objective,
she gave me a goodbye present.
Heroin.
She told me to go shoot up at Insight.
a government-run clinic for injection drug users.
Always controversial,
this experiment has plotted conservatives against liberals,
tangled in debate.
In my opinion,
supervised injection is not medicine.
It does not heal the person addicted to drugs.
Each and every injection...
along with the heroin and cocaine injected harms the person.
And government-sponsored supervised injections sends a very mixed message to young people who are contemplating the illicit use of drugs.
Thank you,
and I'd be happy to take your question.
Given that the insight was peer-reviewed by 21 peer-reviews from international peer-reviews following international principles of research,
did the minister have his report from his advisory council similarly peer-reviewed?
Quick answer,
yes.
Yes or no?
No.
It wasn't for publication.
The minister speaks very much about the fact that this does not work.
Insight was set up to look at a very high risk population of users.
These are the people who will not go to treatment.
These are the people who have the highest incidence of infectious diseases because of the intravenous drug use.
These are the people who needed help and who were dying.
My brother,
the producer of this film,
did not like the idea.
Are you out of your fucking mind?
You're not doing heroin.
Why not?
Why wouldn't I do heroin?
Because it's the most fucking addictive drug,
bitch.
Are you retarded?
I just did crack.
I'm not worried about getting addicted to crack.
You couldn't yet.
I'm not coming back to Hastings a week from now looking for heroin.
Like,
I'm not doing that.
That's ridiculous.
I'm not gonna run back here by myself without you and just go shoot up.
We're doing heroin.
You don't have to do this.
You shouldn't do it.
Yeah.
Well,
that's not true.
no,
it is true.
I should do it.
This is retarded,
Mish.
We're doing it.
You're doing heroin.
No.
Don't.
Fucking stupid.
Well,
we're doing it.
Let's go.
Enter Insight.
This is the first and only safe injection site in North America.
Inside these doors,
users are no longer punishable by drug laws.
They inject their drugs with the help of government-funded medical staff.
This place serves over 600 addicts a day.
Cameras are prohibited here,
so we went undercover.
Turning back now.
Now I'm starting to get scared.
You know,
I was hoping she would break the needle or the cops would come in and shut the place down.
But none of that happened.
Instead,
she just gave me the needle.
And that was on my way.
I'm going to miss the science.
I am the living,
the alive,
the living,
the alive.
I think you can feel that.
Maybe I can.
I'm going to miss you.
The supervised injection site may be the first time that the drug addict comes into contact with healthcare workers who are not judging him and are hostile to him and are trying to change him.
That non-judgmental contact gives people an opportunity to consider addiction in a new light and so harm reduction is not only about specific techniques it's also about meeting people where they are.
How you feeling man?
To be honest,
out of it.
0:40:42.253,0:39:43.094
But I'm cogent.
0:40:44.122,0:39:45.663
Not having difficulty speaking.
But it's not as intense as I would have thought.
Like I'm still
Misha Kleider and I...
Yeah,
I'm not.
It would make you insane or something.
Okay,
come roll.
I want to take you on a magical journey because I know a lot of you are never going to have this experience.
I don't expect a lot of my viewing audience to do heroin.
If I can express this at all well,
Oh boy.
it's like cruising on a cloud.
My legs hurt.
Typically,
my legs don't hurt right now.
The back was cleared right up.
As soon as...
Like before the needle left my arm,
I could feel just...
I could feel the pain in my lower back disappear,
like completely.
Yeah,
it's beautiful.
It's a beautiful experience actually.
But uh,
0:40:47.658,0:39:50.245
I do feel like I'm floating on a cloud.
0:40:51.041,0:39:52.188
It's actually pretty awesome.
0:40:52.188,0:39:54.044
Yeah?
I'm dizzy.
Like I need to puke or something.
Mish,
come on.
Let's go for a walk.
Dude,
seriously?
I don't know why you did that.
It's making me dizzy looking at you.
I feel like there's like little baby ants popping with their fucking eggs underneath my fucking beard or something.
I don't know if I got bullshit stuff or what out,
but honestly...
I'm not feeling any like real cool sensation right now
Like past like the first ten minutes that was nice,
but now I'm just feeling like my skin's all fucking itchy I feel like there's little like ant baby fucking hatchlings under my fucking skin
Especially on my arm right here where that fucking needle went in
Honestly, you can do whatever the fuck you want,
but I'm going home because I'm done with this shit
Keep playing it or whatever,
you can follow me home,
but I'm going home.
I'm not living on the street any longer.
What?
Seriously.
Let's do this.
Five more days,
you can do it.
First of all,
you can't tell me
I have to do it.
You can't fucking tell me that,
cause you're not the one doing this.
I'm the one who's doing this,
right?
I'm the one who has to do all this fucking bullshit.
And it's actually annoying.
You keep on saying,
you know,
all this crap to me.
I'm fucked in the head right now.
I can't even talk straight,
but I'm going home.
I'm done.
Hey.
Wait up,
Come on.
Five more days.
We're not doing this,
Al.
I know,
I know what five more days is gonna do.
But look,
look,
retard,
shut up for a second.
Hey,
hey,
shut up,
hey.
Let me speak for a second,
okay?
42:44.717,0:42:45.743
What's five more days gonna do?
I fucking did the street stint.
I fucking done,
done.
I'm fucking done this shit.
Forking Fuck me You didn't have to fucking do this,
okay?
You observed this shit.
I fucking did it.
So fuck you.
fuck you.
Four days pussy You still wanna do this?
Mish?
Are you sure you wanna quit?
Does it look like I want to quit?
To be honest,
yes,
Alex Alright
Alright.
Fuck it.
Dude,
Let see your eyes.
Are you sure you want to do this man?
Last call bro.
Exactly last call.
Good night.
I passed out as soon as my head hit the pillow.
I then had the worst sleep of my entire life.
I had cold sweats,
I was short of breath,
and I actually looked forward to vomiting because it woke me from the nightmares of the last month.
Then,
the sun hit my face,
and the bad dream was over.
Projects failed.
Right?
I don't know.
Can we salvage this?
What happened?
So has your opinion changed?
Yeah,
yeah.
The problem is just so much more complicated than I initially thought.
And yeah,
I just wrote them off as scammers before for the most part,
Even people that are panhandling and stuff like that,
Like there's some issues they have with them.
If you could boil it all down to just one thing,
one issue,
what would it be?
Addiction.
Addiction is definitely the common thread that unites that whole scene,
you know,
For everybody I met.
I didn't meet anyone that wasn't addicted to something.
I'm not a single person when I think about it actually.
I was addiction free.
The global approach to trying to deal with drugs is headed up by the United Nations Office on Drug
Policy and the International Narcotics Control Board.
Their goal was to one day create a drug-free world,
and I think that's a fantasy.
I think it really illustrates just the magnitude of the problem with addiction,
that it's really the plague of our time.
Capitalist society in a liberal society,
we accept.
That this is not a solvable problem,
but there will always be people that are like leaves in the wind of social pressure.
They'll go the path of least resistance.
And if that path is getting high today,
and the devil they care of tomorrow,
they'll close their eyes and blindly go into that trap.
Given that we live in a culture that is addicted,
as everybody says,
to oil,
where we engage in the pursuit of the amenities and luxuries provided by oil,
Despite the fact that we're destroying the earth,
who are we to tell the addict that they shouldn't be engaging in self-destructive behavior?
In other words,
it's a scapegoat.
We're deeply related to the addict.
We just don't want to see their relationship,
so we ostracize them and banish them to the social periphery.
So,
the experiment is complete.
And what did I find?
Life on the street is easy when you're healthy,
clean,
and living off all the free services.
But the street catches up with you.
And when you're sick and on drugs,
it's a nightmare.
The only difference is that I was able to wake up from it.
I'm left wondering,
is there any hope?
One man seems to think so.
During the completion of this film,
Vancouver voted in a new young mayor.
This is Gregor Robertson,
and this is the best day of his life.
We started this campaign by talking about homelessness,
and tonight I'm going to finish right where I started.
We are going to end homelessness in Vancouver.
Like you,
I have one simple question.
How?
The most economical way to do this and the most just way to do this is to focus on housing and health care supports attached to that housing.
It'll be more affordable and it'll be better life for thousands of people in Vancouver.
I lived on the streets for almost a month.
I tried the hardest drugs out there,
crack,
heroin.
One thing that became very clear was that addiction is a major cause of homelessness.
So if you're going to solve homelessness,
you need to solve addiction.
The addiction challenge is very difficult for us.
It's a tough one to break,
and we're seeing some success now with the show.
Shelters and basically saying it's okay,
you can come in if you're still using,
you can use these shelters to at least get a good meal and get eight hours of sleep.
But 95%
of addiction treatments fail.
And what's going to happen when you provide all these homeless addicts with free housing?
Instead of dying from their addiction on the street,
they're going to die from addiction in the free homes that you're giving them.
but they're still going to die.
That seems like a band-aid and not a solution.
Well,
it's a band-aid,
but if people are literally dying on the streets,
you've got to look at what pieces you can support them on.
I mean,
if you don't come in with a whole...
complement of support then then where's the hope until you work upstream until we're working with people and making making sure they don't go into that dead end of addiction you know it's going to be damage control yeah do you honestly think that you can end
When I say end homelessness or that we do a lot better on addictions and for treatment,
there's just so much more that can be done.
And can we ever get all the way there and into utopia?
Let's be realistic.
It's not going to be like that.
We've got to have shelters and housing options that are permissive and that take people where they are and meet them where they're at.
Good luck.
Do I believe you will succeed?
I wish I could.
But the fact is,
in the heart of my perfect city exists a ten-block hell of drugs,
death,
disease,
and destitution.
Despite billions spent on services for the homeless,
they have not slowed the plague of addiction.
It is this self-imposed slavery that perpetuates homelessness.
And it's a slavery that no government,
no doctor,
and no bed will ever end.
Only they themselves can do it.
Most die before they get the chance.
So.
If you come here.
And get addicted.
You stay here.
You do stay here.
Are the streets...
Of plenty.